Guide to the Lester Frank Ward papers, 1883-1919 MS0247.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Lester Frank Ward papers
1883-1919
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Ward, Lester Frank
MS0247.UA
2 Linear Feet
Lester Frank Ward (1841-1913) has been described by some as the father of American sociology. His contributions to sociology are almost forgotten today, but at one time he was considered to be one of America's leading intellectuals. Collection includes diaries, correspondence, photographs, a scrapbook. and sixty-nine articles written by Lester Frank Ward. The materials range in date from between 1883 and 1919.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Provenance of this collection is unknown.
Biographical Note
Lester Frank Ward (1841-1913), described by some as the father of American sociology, was born June 18, 1841 in Joliet, Illinois. The Ward family was not wealthy so there was no extra money with which to send Lester to school for a formal education. Instead, Ward was self educated in his youth. Some reports indicate that Ward taught himself many languages including Latin, Greek and German, and could read Russian, Japanese and Hebrew. His studies also included mathematics and geology.
His contributions to sociology are almost forgotten today, but at one time he was considered to be one of America's leading intellectuals. The Ward family moved from Illinois to Myersburg, Pennsylvania while Frank was still young. By day Ward joined his brother Cyrenus in their wagon wheel shop.
By night he devoured books and developed a craving for knowledge and study. Some believe that Ward's childhood spent in poverty, followed later by hard labor in the wagon shop, instilled in Ward an outrage at society's injustice and inequalities. In the early 1860's Ward attended classes at the Susquehana Collegiate Institute in Towanada.
On August 13, 1862 he married Elizabeth "Lizzie" Caroline Bought. When the Civil War broke out, Ward joined a local Pennsylvania regiment and was seriously wounded at Chancellorville. Like many soldiers away from home to fight in the war, Ward kept a journal which is still available today under the title Young Ward's Diary. Some of his thinking about society and inequality developed further during his Civil War experience.
After the war he began working for the federal government while continuing his education. From 1865 to 1881 Ward was employed by the United States Treasury Department. During this period he studied at Columbian College (now George Washington University) from which he received the A.B. degree in 1869, the LL.B. degree in 1871, and the A.M. degree in 1872. He received an honorary Doctor of Laws from the university in 1898. In 1882 Ward was appointed assistant geologist for the U.S. Geological Survey, a post he held for two years. He served the USGS for the remainder of his career in the federal government, receiving promotions to Geologist in 1889, and Paleontologist in 1892.
In addition to his USGS work, Ward was appointed Honorary Curator of the Department of Fossil Plants in the US National Museum in 1882. He remained in charge of the national collections of fossil plants until his resignation from the USGS in 1905. In that year he accepted a faculty appointment at Brown University, where he remained until his death.
Ward is best remembered for his pioneering work in sociology. Between 1883 and his death in 1913, he completed several important works including Dynamic Sociology (1883), Outlines of Sociology (1898), Pure Sociology (1903), and Applied Sociology (1906).
His book Dynamic Sociology was revolutionary, arguing that progress depended on a planned society led and controlled by a benevolent government, that provided universal education, freedom from poverty and happiness for all. When this book was first published, courses in sociology were nonexistent in American universities, and by the time the second edition was published in 1896, sociology was being taught in all colleges.
Ward supported the idea of equality of women as well as the equality of all classes and races in society. He believed in universal education as a means of achieving this equality. Many of his ideas were unpopular among his male contemporaries, but would probably play better to an audience today. In 1906 and 1907, Ward served as the first President of the American Sociological Society (now known as the American Sociological Association). He also served as the editor of the American Journal of Sociology starting in 1905.
The eminent historian Henry Steele Commager said, "In perspicacity, intellectual acumen and imagination, Lester Frank Ward takes place alongside William James, John Dewey and Oliver Wendell Holmes as one of the creative spirits of 20th century America.
Lester Ward died April 18, 1913.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include diaries, correspondence, photographs, a scrapbook. and sixty-nine articles written by Lester Frank Ward. The materials range in date from between 1883 and 1919.
Collection Organization
Organized in two series: Personal papers and Articles.
Photographs; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Sociology; Biography; Scrapbooks; Washington (D.C.); Diaries; Columbian University; George Washington University; George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae; Ward, Lester Frank
- Personal papers, 1883-1919; MS0247 Series 1; 1.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of diaries, correspondence, photographs and a scrapbook.
  - Diaries: Lester Frank Ward's record of work and principal events, 07/1890-06/30/1897 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diaries: Lester Frank Ward's record of work, 07/01/1897-12/31/1905 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Diaries: Lester Frank Ward's record of work, 1909-1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diaries: Diary of Lester Frank Ward, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 06/27/1883 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    General note
    Hatcheson was reading room Superintendent at the Library of Congress.
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 09/27/1888 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: U.S. Geological Survey., 11/10/1888 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: U.S. Geological Survey., 01/16/1889 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 08/31/1890 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 01/14/1892 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 07/12/1893 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 07/12/1893 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Page 2 of letter. Hatcheson was reading room Superintendent at the Library of Congress.
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 12/24/1893 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 05/30/1896 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinsonn: The Magnolia, Washington, D.C., 12/29/1900 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 10/26/1904 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson:, 11/09/1904 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson, 11/22/1904 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson, 12/17/1904 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Postcard. Hatcheson was reading room Superintendent at the Library of Congress.
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson, 03/25/1905 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 03/25/1905 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 03/25/1905 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Page 3 of letter. Hatcheson was reading room Superintendent at the Library of Congress.
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson, 03/25/1905 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Page 4 of letter. Hatcheson was reading room Superintendent at the Library of Congress.
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 06/20/1905 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 03/07/1905 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 03/17/1905 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 03/31/1905 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence with David Hutchinson: Washington, D.C., 02/17/1906 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence: Brown University, Rhode Island, 09/28/1912 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: from Ernst Haeckel, German biologist, to Lester Ward's sister, 05/24/1913 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Photographs: Portrait of Lester Ward,age 45, 09/08/1886 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Photographs: View of the house in which Lester Frank Ward was born, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Photographs: Portrait of Lester Ward, age 29, 06/12/1869 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Photographs: Portrait of Lester Ward, age 36, 01/16/1878 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Photographs: Frontis piece portrait of Lester Ward, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Photographs: Portrait of Lester Ward, 06/12/1849 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Duplicate of 31
  - Photographs: View of Ward in the field, Kansas, 09/05/1898 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Photographs: View of Ward in his Office at the Smitsonian, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Photographs: View of Ward in the field, Kansas, 09/05/1898 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Articles, Flyers, and Correspondence by and about Lester Ward, 1913-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Articles by Lester Ward, 1889-1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Articles by Lester Ward, 1890-1913 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Articles by Lester Ward, 1890-1913 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook [currently missing], 1841-1913 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Scrapbook contains clippings about Ward, obituaries, and articles by Ward. Holograph and typed sympathy letters (mostly) to Rosamond A. Ward (Mrs. Lester Ward) from scholars. Representative names include: Paul Barth, Camile Fontaine, Franklin Henry Giddings, Dennis Hied, Albert Galloway Keller, Herbert Putnam, Ferdinand Tonnies, Rossamond Ward, Rene Worms.
- Articles, 1888-1913; MS0247 Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series consists of sixty-nine articles written by Lester Frank Ward. They are contained in three bound volumes and range in date from 1888-1913.
  - Volume 1: Static and Dynamic Sociology, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Volume 1: Natural Storage of Energy, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Volume 1: The Place of Sociology Among the Sciences, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Volume 1: Saporta and Williamson and their Work in Paleobotany, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Volume 1: Sociology and Cosmology, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Volume 1: Plutocracy and Paternalism, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Volume 1: Sociology and Biology, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Volume 1: Fossil Plants, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Volume 1: Sociology and Anthropology, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Volume 1: Sociology and Psychology; and A Review of Dr. Patten's Theory of Social Forces, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Volume 1: The Data of Sociology, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Volume 1: The Principles of Sociology, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Volume 1: Ethical Aspects of Social Science, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Volume 1: The Social Forces, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Volume 1: The Mechanics of Society, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Volume 1: The Purpose of Sociology; and A Review of Roberty's Le Bien et Le Mal, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Volume 1: Discussion and Correspondence: Age of Island Series, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Volume 1: Social Genesis, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Volume 1: Individual Telesis, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Volume 1: Descriptions of the Species of Cycadeoidea, or Fossil Cycadean Trunks, thus far Discovered in the Iron Ore Belt, Potomac Formation, of Maryland, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Volume 1: Collective Telesis, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Volume 1: Sociology, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Volume 1: Review of Organsime et Societe and La Pathologie Sociale, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Volume 1: Prof. Fontaine and Dr. Newberry on the Age of the Potomac Formation, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Volume 1: L'Economie de la Douleur et L'Economie du Plaisir, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Volume 1: The Essential Nature of Religion, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Volume 1: Utilitarian Economics, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Volume 1: Descriptions of the Species of Cyadeoidea, or Fossil Cycadean Trunks, thus far Determined from the Lower Cretaceous Rim of the Black Hills, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Volume 1: Truth and Error, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Volume 1: Review of Ward's paper "The Filiation of the Sciences", 1896 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Volume 2: Book Review, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Volume 2: Frost Freaks of the Dittany, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Volume 2: The New Botany, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Volume 2: Herbert Spencer's Sociology, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Volume 2: Report on the Petrified Forests of Arizona, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Volume 2: The Value of Error, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Volume 2: The Greatest Living Man, by William Jackson Armstrong, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Volume 2: Recent Discoveries of Cyadean Trunks in the Potaomac Formation of Maryland, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Volume 2: Fossil Cycadean Trunks of North America, with a Revision of the Genus Cycadeoidea Buckland, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Volume 2: The Exemption of Women from Labor, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Volume 2: The Monistic Theory of Mind, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Volume 2: Status of the Mind Problem 1894 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Volume 2: Childhood, 1892 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Volume 2: Address to the American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1892 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Volume 2: Principles and Methods of Geological Correlation by Means of Fossil Plants, 1892 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Volume 2: Lecture: Status of the Mind Problem, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Volume 2: Political Ethics of Herbert Spencer, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Volume 2: Book review by Ward, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Volume 2: The Science and Art of Government, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Volume 2: The Transmission of Culture, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Volume 2: The Plant-Bearing Deposits of the American Trias, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Volume 2: Origin of the Plant-Trees, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Volume 2: Address: The Course of Biological Evolution, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Volume 2: Causes of Belief in Immortality, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Volume 2: The Sociological Position of Protection and Free Trade, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Volume 2: The Paleontologic History of the Genus Platanus, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Volume 2: The Nomenclature Question, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Volume 2: Remarks on the Undescribed Vegetable Organism from the Fort Union Group of Montana, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Volume 2: Proceedings of New York Geological Society meeting, undated (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Volume 3: Publication memo regarding "The Life and Works of Lester F. Ward", undated (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Volume 3: Le Progres Spontane et Le Progres Voluntaire, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Volume 3: Geology of the Little Colorado Valley, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Volume 3: Contemporary Sociology, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Volume 3: Mecanique Sociale, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Volume 3: Sociology at the Paris Exposition of 1900, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Volume 3: Elaboration of the Fossil Cycads in the Yale Museum, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Volume 3: Review: The Theory of the Leisure Class. An Economic Study in the Evolution of Institutions, by Thorstein Veblen, undated (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Volume 3: Review: Social Laws, an Outline of Sociology, by G. Tarde, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Volume 3: Description of a New Genus and Twenty New Species of Fossil Cycadean Trunks from the Jurassic of Wyoming, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 69)